Finding Aid for the Gilbert A. Harrison collection of material by and relating to Gertrude Stein LSC.2108
UCLA Library Special Collections
Gilbert A. Harrison collection of material by and relating to Gertrude Stein
1922-1984
UCLA Library Special Collections
Harrison, Gilbert A.
LSC.2108
3.5 Linear Feet (7 boxes, 2 oversize boxes)
Gilbert Harrison was a UCLA alumnus and former editor-in-chief of The New Republic magazine. He began corresponding with Gertrude Stein in 1933, and continued to correspond with Stein until her death in 1947. The collection contains galley and page proofs for books by and about Stein, documents regarding the Stein estate, correspondence, manuscripts, photographs, objects, tape recordings, film, graphics, theatre programs, and exhibition catalogs. Correspondence from Alice B. Toklas, and articles about her, are also included.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Gilbert A. Harrison, 1973-88.
Bulk of collection was received from Harrison; consult finding aid for additional information.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9917203653606533
Biography
Gilbert Harrison, UCLA alumnus and former editor-in-chief of The new republic magazine, began corresponding with Gertrude Stein in 1933, and met her at a lecture in Pasadena, California, in 1934; Harrison visited Stein and Alice B. Toklas at their home in France in 1937, when Stein presented him with the typescript of The autobiography of Alice B. Toklas; Harrison continued to correspond with Stein until her death in 1947, and maintained a friendship with Toklas until her death in 1967.
Scope and Content
Collection contains galley and page proofs for books by and about Stein, and documents regarding the Stein estate. Also includes correspondence, manuscripts, photographs, objects, tape recordings, film, graphics, theatre programs, and exhibition catalogs. Correspondence from Alic B. Toklas and articles about her are included. Original works of art, including an original oil painting of Alice B. Toklas by Pavel Tchelitchev, are cataloged separately.
Expanded Scope and Content Note
Gilbert Harrison, UCLA alumnus and former editor-in-chief of the New Republic, first met Gertrude Stein in 1934, in Pasadena, California. Harrison, who had corresponded with Stein since 1933, and fellow UCLA students Hal Levy and Bill Okie, attended Stein's lecture at the Women's Club in Pasadena. The three students were so fascinated by Stein and her approach to literature and art that they followed her after the lecture to the Huntington Hotel where she was staying. After introducing themselves to her, Stein prevailed upon them to share a few moments conversation which lasted until early morning.
The acquaintance was renewed in 1937 when Harrison visited Stein and Alice B. Toklas at Bilignin. It was at this time that Stein presented the typescript for The autobiography of Alice B. Toklas to him. Their friendship and correspondence continued until her death in 1946. Harrison continued to correspond with Alice and maintained a warm, affectionate friendship with her until her death in 1967.
The Gilbert Harrison collection of Steiniana is a rich source of information for one of the most unique and controversial literary figures of the 20th century. It includes books by and about Stein, original works of art, correspondence from Stein and Toklas and others, manuscripts, galley and page proofs for books by and about Stein, photographs, documents concerning the Stein estate, objects, tape recordings, film, graphics, articles by and about Stein, theatre programs and exhibition catalogs. Harrison's collection of books by and about Stein have been, cataloged individually and are listed in the Rare Book Catalog, Department of Special Collections. Original works of art are listed in the Numbered Collections Catalog, Department of Special Collections.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Correspondence (Box 1).
Manuscripts (Box 2).
Documents, ephemera, tape recordings, film (Box 3).
Photographs, graphics, published articles by Stein (Box 4).
Articles about Stein and/or Toklas (Box 5).
Letters and typecripts (Box 6).
Letters from Stein and Toklas (Box 7).
Scrapbooks (Box 8).
Photograph of plaque, typescripts of Identity and related correspondence (Box 9).
Separated Materials
Portrait of Alice B. Toklas (55 × 40cm. Ink drawing, Framed, 73 × 58 cm.) [oversize]. Picture Collection (Collection 99). Department of Special Collections, University Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
Gertrude Stein (20cm. Bronze sculpture) [oversize]. Picture Collection (Collection 99). Department of Special Collections, University Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
Gertrude Stein (102.5 × 82cm. Oil portrait, Framed, 115.5 × 100cm.). Picture Collection (Collection 99). Department of Special Collections, University Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
Alice B. Toklas (30cm. Pencil sketch profile portrait, Framed, 57.5 × 45cm.). Picture Collection (Collection 99). Department of Special Collections, University Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
The house at Bilignin (27.5 × 42.5cm. Oil painting). Picture Collection (Collection 99). Department of Special Collections, University Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
Alice B. Toklas (75 × 40cm. Oil portrait, Framed, 87 × 52cm.) ORIG. 99
The making of Americans. Gertrude Stein read by Marian Seldes (2 s. 12in. 33 1/3 rpm record). Collection of Miscellaneous Phonograph Records (Collection 249, Box 12). Department of Special Collections, University Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
Gertrude Stein read by Gertrude Stein (2 s. 12 in. 33 1/3 rpm record). Collection of Miscellaneous Phonograph Records (Collection 249, Box 12). Department of Special Collections, University Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
Online Items Available
Portions of this collection have been digitized and are available online: Gilbert A. Harrison Collection of Material by and Relating to Gertrude Stein (18 items).
Index to Manuscripts, Photographs, Recordings
Alsop, Joseph Wright, 1910- Box 1, folder 21
Balmain, Pierre, 1914- Box 4, folder 5
Beach, Sylvia, 1887-1962 Box 1, folder 10
Beaton, Cecil Walter Hardy, 1904- Box 4, folder 3
Bowles, Paul Frederic, 1911- Box 1, folder 22
Breon, John Box 4, folder 8
Brown, Robert Carlton, 1886-1959 Box 6, folder 16
Burns, Edward Box 2, folder 6
Davidson, Jo, 1883-1952 Box 4, folder 13
Delar, Sophie Box 4, folder 1
Gorey, Edward St. John Box 4, folder 18
Haas, Robert Bartlett Box 2, folder 8; Box 8
Harrison, Gilbert A Box 1, folders 1, 3-19; Box 2, folder 9; Box 4, folder 19; Box 5, folder 27-28
Kapton, Constantinoff Box 1, folder 23
Katz, Leon, 1919- Box 2, folders 6, 10
Kazin, Alfred, 1915- Box 8
Knapik, Harold Box 1, folder 20
Knapik, Virginia Box 1, folder 20; Box 3, folder 5
Moore, Honor, 1915- Box 2, folder 11
Picabia, Francis, 1878-1946 Box 6, folder 29
Rea, Joy Box 6, folders 18-27.
Rogers, William Garland, 1896- Box 4, folder 2
Rose, Sir Francis Cyril, Bart., 1909- Box 1, folders 24-25; Box 6, folder 5-6, 10
Seldes, Marian Box 3, folder 1
Stein, Gertrude, 1874-1946 Box 1, folders 1-2, 27; Box 2, folder 1-5; Box 3, folder 7-8, 10; Box 4, folder 1-2, 9-13, 16-30; Box 5, folder 29; Box 6, folder 6-12, 15-16
Stein family Box 3, folder 10
Sutherland, Donald Box 6, folder 14
Tchelitchew, Pavel, 1898-1957 Box 6, folder 15
Thomson, Virgil, 1896- Box 6, folder 28
Toklas, Alice Babette, 1877-1967 Box 1, folders 3-19; Box 2, folder 7; Box 3, folder 2,4; Box 4, folder 3-11, 15-17; Box 6, folder 6, 13-14, 18-26
Toklas family Box 4, folder 12
Van Vechten, Carl, 1880-1964 Box 1, folder 27; Box 4, folder 8-9; Box 5, folder 29; Box 6, folder 7
Wilder, Thornton Niven, 1897-1975 Box 4, folder 7
Added Entries
Alsop, Joseph Wright, 1910-
Beaton, Cecil Walter Hardy, 1904-
Bowles, Paul Frederic, 1911-
Breon, John
Brown, Robert Carlton, 1886-1959
Burns, Edward
Delar, Sophie
Gorey, Edward St. John
Haas, Robert Bartlett
Katz, Leon, 1919-
Kazin, Alfred, 1915-
Knapik, Harold
Knapik, Virginia
Moore, Honor, 1915-
Rose, Sir Francis Cyril, Bart., 1909-
Stein, Gertrude, 1874-1946
Tchelitchew, Pavel, 1898-1957
Toklas, Alice Babette
Van Vechten, Carl, 1880-1964
Thomson, Virgil, 1896-
Rea, Joy
Picabia, Francis, 1878-1946
Subject Entries
American literature - 20th century.
Authors, American - Correspondence, reminiscences, etc.
Balmain, Pierre, 1914 -- Portrait.
Beach, Sylvia, 1867-1962.
Book-plates - Specimens.
Davidson, Jo, 1883-1952.
Rogers, Willia, Garland, 1896-
Stein, Gertrude, 1874-1946.
Stein, Gertrude, 1874-1946 - Portrait.
Sutherland, Donald, 1915-
Toklas, Alice Babette
Toklas, Alice Babette - Portrait.
Van Vechten, Carl, 1880-1964 - Portrait
Wilder Thornton Niven, 1897-1975 - Portrait.
Americans in Paris.
Women authors, American -- France -- Paris -- Archives.; Stein, Gertrude, 1874-1946--Archives.; Toklas, Alice, B.--Archives.
- Correspondence
  - Letters to Gilbert Harrison. v.p., 1934-1937, n.d.; 13 items (16 leaves, 10 envelopes). Holograph. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    Some of these letters were removed from the typescript manuscript of The autobiography of Alice B. Toklas.
  - Letter to Mrs. Paulaine Novak. Paris, 1945.; 1 item (1 leaf, 1 envelope). Holograph. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Scope and Contents note
    With this: Photograph of Mrs. Novak with her dog.
  - Letters to Gilbert Harrison. v.p., n.d.; 8 items (3 cards, 4 letters, 1 telegram). Holograph. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letter to Gilbert Harrison. Paris, 30 December 1933.; 1 item (1 leaf, 1 envelope). Typescript (signed). (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters to Gilbert Harrison. Paris, 1949.; 2 items (2 leaves, 1 envelope). Holograph. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letter to Gilbert Harrison. Paris, 1950.; 1 item (1 leaf, 1 envelope). Holograph. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters to Gilbert Harrison. Paris, 1951.; 1 item (1 leaf) Holograph. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letters to Gilbert Harrison. Paris, 1952.; 2 items (1 card, 1 leaf) Holograph. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letters to Gilbert and Nancy Harrison. Paris, 1953.; 5 items (6 leaves) Holograph. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letters to Gilbert and Nancy Harrison. Paris, 1954.; 5 items (10 leaves) Holograph. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    This includes a 3pp. (3 leaves) holograph reminiscence by Toklas of Sylvia Beach's bookshop.
  - Letters to Gilbert and Nancy Harrison. Paris, 1955.; 12 items (1 card, 11 leaves) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letters to Gilbert and Nancy Harrison. Paris, 1956.; 2 items (2 leaves) Holograph. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Letters to Gilbert and Nancy Harrison. Paris, 1956.; 14 items (23 leaves) Holograph. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Letters to Gilbert and Nancy Harrison. Paris, 1958.; 10 items (13 leaves, 1 envelope). Holograph. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Letters to Gilbert and Nancy Harrison, v.p., 1959.; 7 items (8 leaves) Holograph. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Letters to Gilbert and Nancy Harrison. v.p., 1960.; 3 items (6 leaves, 1 envelope). Holograph. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Letters to Gilbert and Nancy Harrison. v.p., 1961.; 6 items (8 leaves) Holograph. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Letters of 17 January 1961 and 28 August 1961 dictated to Jo Barry.
  - Letters to Gilbert and Nancy Harrison. v.p., 1962.; 2 items (2 leaves) Holograph. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Letter of 7 July 1962 dictated to "DS."
  - Letters to Gilbert and Nancy Harrison. Paris, 1963.; 4 items (8 leaves) Holograph. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Letter of 10 January 1963 dictated to Jo Barry.
    Total number of Toklas/Harrison letter: 85.
  - Letters to Harold and Virginia Knapik. v.p., 1958-1966.; 8 items (11 leaves, 3 envelopes). Holograph. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Letters of 9 January 1965 and 2 January 1966 are in another hand.
  - Letter to Gilbert Harrison. Washington, D.C., 1974.; 1 item (1 leaf) Typescript (signed). (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Letter to Gilbert Harrison. Tangier, 1972.; 1 item (1 leaf) Typescript (signed). (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Telegram to Gilbert Harrison. Paris, 1967. (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Telegram informing Harrison of the death of Alice B. Toklas.
  - Christmas greeting. London, 1 item (1 leaf) Holograph. (Box 1, Folder 24)
    On black and white drawing of a cat (Photocopy).
  - [Drawing of Alice B. Toklas] n.p., n.d.; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Signed "Mlle. Toklas/ 'faite le marche rue Christine'/Francis Rose." Black ballpoint pen.
  - Letter to Mr. Evett. New York, March 14, 1957.; 1 item (1 leaf) Typescript (signed). (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Manuscripts
  - The autobiography of Alice B. Toklas. n.p., n.d.; [4], [246pp.] Typescript with holograph corrections. Inscribed on title page "For Gilbert Harrison from Gtde Stein." Bound in dark blue cloth. (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Note: Letters originally tipped into the back of the manuscript have been removed and integrated with the correspondence section. These letters were from Gertrude Stein and Alice B. Toklas.
  - Fernhurst and other early writings, n.p., 1969.; 262 leaves. Photocopy. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    This was published under the title Fernhurst, Q.E.D. and other early writings (New York, Liveright [c1971]). With introduction by Leon Katz.
    The pieces by Stein were published in a different order than this photocopy.
  - Fernhurst, Q.E.D. and other early writings., pp.43-248. Photocopy. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Page proofs with proofreader's marks.
  - Galleys., 65 leaves. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    With printer's marks.
  - Page proofs (for introduction by Leon Katz)., 46 leaves. Photocopy. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    With manuscript corrections and proofreader's marks.
  - Picasso. If I told him (A complete portrait of Picasso)., Page proofs. 60 leaves. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    With proofreader's marks. Text for Gertrude Stein on Picasso (New York, Liveright [c1970]). Edited by Edward Burns. Afterword by Leon Katz and Edward Burns.
  - "They walk in the light.", 13 leaves. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Typescript with manuscript corrections and proofreader's marks. Afterword for Gertrude Stein on Picasso.
    With this: Acknowledgments (2 leaves) and A note on the text (4 leaves).
  - "Tape--readings by Alice B. Toklas from her cookbook." n.p., n.d.; 13 leaves. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Typescript with manuscript corrections (transcription).
  - "Still another garland for Gertrude Stein." Los Angeles, 29 leaves. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Typescript. Lacking pp.11-18, 35-36.
  - [Introduction] n.p., n.d.; 5 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 2, Folder 9)
    This appeared in Gertrude Stein's America (Washington, D.C., Robert B. Luce, Incorporated [1965]), edited by Gilbert Harrison.
  - The making of Americans. Pittsburgh, c1972.; 90 leaves. Typescript (photocopy). (Box 2, Folder 10)
    "An opera and play by Leon Katz from the novel by Gertrude Stein."
  - "Poems of Gertrude Stein and selections from Poetry and grammar." New York, 1973.; 77 leaves Typescript and typescript (photocopy). (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Orchestrated by ARW with Honor Moore.
    With this: Letter of transmittal, 22 January 1974, from Honor Moore to Gilbert Harrison.
- Documents
  - Estate of Gertrude Stein and related documents. v.p., v.d.; 9 items. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Includes:
    1) Last will and testament of Gertrude Stein. Paris, 23 July 1946 (5 leaves Thermofax copy).
    2) First administration account of the estate of Gertrude Stein. Baltimore, 4 May 1948 (8 leaves Thermofax).
    3) Third administration account of the estate of Gertrude Stein. Baltimore, 22 June 1951 (4 leaves Thermofax copy).
    4) Memorandum by Douglas Rigler re administration of the Stein estate. Baltimore, 23 February 1965 (4 leaves Thermofax copy).
    5) Petition for appointment of conservator. Ex parte in the matter of Alice B. Toklas. Baltimore, 1961 (3 leaves Thermofax copy).
    6) Summary of tax questions (2 leaves photocopy).
    7) Schedule of property (1 leaf photocopy).
    8) Administrator's inventory (1 leaf photocopy).
    9) Letter from Daniel C. Joseph, administrator of the Stein estate, to Russell M. Porter. 30 August 1965 (1 leaf photocopy). With copy of letter from Joseph to Daniel C. Stern. 3 August 1905 (2 leaves photocopy).
  - Obituaries regarding the death of Alice B. Toklas. v.p., 1967.; 2 items. (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Objects
  - Blue leather portfolio with gold tooling belonging to Gertrude Stein(?)., 25.4 × 34.2 cm. 1 item. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Silk handkerchief embroidered by Alice B. Toklas "Rose is a rose is a rose is a rose," surrounding a rose., White on white. 28 × 26 cm. The embroidery itself measures 1.5 cm. diameter. In Marshall Field & Company box. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Eighteenth century paste necklace., Length: 34.5 cm. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Bought by Gertrude Stein for Alice B. Toklas, who upon Stein's death, gave the necklace to Virginia Knapik. The necklace is composed of a series of pink and green center stones, surrounded by rhinestones, with 1 large design hanging from the center as a pendant. Several stones are missing. In Tessier Limited, London, case.
  - Novelty flags., 2 items. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    French and American flags used in the Gertrude Stein exhibit (UCLA Library, 1974).
  - Novelty T-shirt with portrait of Gertrude Stein on the front., 1 item. (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Tape Recordings
  - Tape recording., 7 inch reel. Speed 3/4, track 1/2. (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Band 1. Gertrude Stein read by Gertrude Stein.
    Missing Title
    1. "The making of Americans."
    2. "A valentine to Sherwood Anderson."
    3. "If I told him (A complete portrait of Picasso)."
    4. "Matisse."
    5. "Madame Recamier" (An opera).
    Band 2. The making of Americans by Gertrude Stein, read by Marian Seldes. With this: Printed text to accompany Folkway Records, Album no.FL9742. New York, c1963.
  - Tape recording., 7 inch reel. Speed 3/4, track 1/2. (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Four Saints in Three Acts (libretto by Gertrude Stein, music by Virgil Thomson) and Capital, Capitals (words by Gertrude Stein, music by Virgil Thomson).
- Film
  - [Gertrude Stein and family. Paris, ]., ca. 1920s-1930s?; 16mm. Running time: ca. 5 minutes. (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Home movies of Gertrude Stein.
    The original film was given to Yale University by Julian S. Stein, Jr., from which this copy was made.
- Photographs (Listed by Subject)
  - Gertrude Stein. Black/white proofs by Sophie Delar. n.p., n.d.; 5 items. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    With this: Letter of transmittal from Delar to Gilbert Harrison, 27 November 1970 (1 leaf).
  - "Gertrude Stein at her summer home in Bilignin." Photograph taken by W.G. Rogers. Bilignin, ca. 193_.; Black/white copy print. 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Alice B.Toklas. Photographs by Cecil Beaton. [London, ]., 1936; Black/white photographs. 2 items. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Alice B. Toklas. v.p., v.d.; Black/white photographs. 4 items. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Alice B. Toklas and Pierre Balmain. n.p., Black/white copy prints. 2 items. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Alice B. Toklas and an unknown woman. v.p., v.d.; Black/white photographs. 4 items. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Alice B. Toklas and Thornton Wilder. Chicago, 1934.; Black/white copy print. 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 7)
    On the left is Mrs. Charles B. Goodspeed.
  - Alice B. Toklas and Carl Van Vechten. Photograph taken by John Breon. Chartes, October 8, 1949.; Black/white photograph (postcard). 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Gertrude Stein and Alice B. Toklas. Photographs taken by Carl Van Vechten. v.p., 1934-1935.; Black/white photographs. 6 items. (Box 4, Folder 9)
    1) Gertrude Stein. Luce(?) Church, June 13, 1934.
    2) Alice B. Toklas. [New York], November 1934.
    3) Alice B. Toklas. [New York], 4 November 1934.
    4) Alice B. Toklas. New York, 4 November 1934.
    5) Alice B. Toklas. Richmond, Virginia, 7 February 1935. In the garden of the Poe Shrine.
    6) Alice B. Toklas. New York, 2 May 1935.
  - Gertrude Stein and Alice B. Toklas. v.p., v.d.; Black/white copy prints. 8 items. (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Photographs
  - "American volunteers and their French friends in World War I." n.p.(France), ca. 1917[?].; Black/white copy print. 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 11)
    Alice B. Toklas, extreme left, Gertrude Stein, extreme right.
    Original photograph is in the Yale collection of American literature, the Gertrude Stein Collection.
  - Toklas family. n.p., n.d.; Black/white copy prints. 2 items. (Box 4, Folder 12)
    Includes a photograph of Mrs. Simon Toklas, Alice's mother.
  - Gertrude Stein by Jo Davidson, n.p., ca. 1923.; Black/white photographs of the bronze sculpture by Davidson. 2 items. (Box 4, Folder 13)
    The sculpture itself is in the Department of Special Collections, UCLA (cataloged *ORIG. 99).
  - Gertrude Stein with soldiers. v.p., v.d.; Black/white copy prints. 6 items. (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Alice B. Toklas with Picasso's portrait of Gertrude Stein. n.p., n.d.; Black/white copy print. 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Various photographs, v.p., v.d.; Negatives. 7 items. (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Alice B. Toklas and Gertrude Stein in the sitting room at Bilignin., ca. 1936.; Black/white copy print. 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 17)
    Print of a painting by Sir Francis Rose.
- Graphics
  - "Gertrude Stein as a child decorates a dog for Christmas." n.p. [Albondocani Press, ]., December 1975; 1 item. Pen and ink drawing on a yellow card. Limited edition of 400 copies. With envelope. (Box 4, Folder 18)
    Christmas card.
  - Bookplate [for Gilbert Harrison]., 9 × 13.5 cm. Linocut, Black on very dark blue. With Harrison's signature. (Box 4, Folder 19)
    Gertrude Stein with a rose and halo.
- Articles by Stein
  - [Book review of Oscar Wilde discovers America by Lloyd Lewis and Harold Justin Smith]. Chicago Daily Tribune ()., August 8, 1936; p.9. Photocopy. (Box 4, Folder 20)
    Column is titled "Gertrude Stein praises Lewis' picture of U.S."
  - "Description of literature," Transition, no.13 ()., Summer 1928; pp.50-55. (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - "I came and here I am," Hearst's International Cosmopolitan, (February 1955).; pp.[18]-19, 167. Clipping. (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - "The making of Americans. Being the history of a family's progress," The Transatlantic Review, vol.1, no.6, (July 1924).; pp.392-405. (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - "The new hope in 'our sad young men'," The New York Times Magazine, (June 3, 1945).; pp.5-[38] Photocopy. (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - ["Reflection on the atomic bomb"], Yale Poetry Review, no.7, (1947).; pp.3-4. (Box 4, Folder 25)
    With this: "Sonnets that please," poem by Gertrude Stein (Photocopy).
  - "We are back in Paris." In: Transformation three. [London]: Lindsay Drummond Limited, [1945].; pp.5-9. (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - "The winner loses. A picture of Occupied France," The Atlantic, (November 1940).; pp.571-583. (Box 4, Folder 27)
- Articles by Gertrude Stein
  - ["The paintings of Elie Lascaux. Preface."] Bilignin, 6 August 1935.; 3 leaves Photocopy of the published item. (Box 4, Folder 28)
    Written for a catalogue accompanying an exhibition of Laxcaux's paintings at the Arts Club, Chicago.
  - "Picabia. Stanza LXXI." n.p., 1936.; 3 leaves Photocopy of published poem. (Box 4, Folder 29)
    Published in a catalogue accompanying an exhibition of Francis Picabia's paintings at the Arts Club, Chicago, 1936.
  - ["The works of Sir Francis Rose. Foreword."] n.p., 1934.; 5 leaves Photocopy of the published item. (Box 4, Folder 30)
    Written by Stein for a catalogue accompanying an exhibition of Rose's paintings at the Arts Club, Chicago, November 1934.
- Articles about Gertrude Stein and/or Alice B. Toklas
  - "Paris á table: A memory of Alice B. Toklas," Gourmet, (August 1967).; pp.13, 28, 30. Clipping. (Box 5, Folder 1)